

□ 216-544-8680 | **☑** itsxiaoliu.cs@gmail.com | **ਕ** xiao-liu.me | **回** liuxiao1468 | **⊡** xiao-leo-liu-1a5bb3112

# Summary.

I am a Computer Science Ph.D candidate and I work with **Prof. Heni Ben Amor** at Interactive Robotics Lab in School of Computing and Augmented Intelligence at Arizona State University. My research is focusing on Robot Learning, Representation Learning, and their applications in Embodied AI and Human-robot Interaction (HRI). Several publications of my research are/were shown at **ICRA**, **IROS**, and **CoRL**. Currently, my research interests are exploring methods to empower large language models (LLMs) to operate as reasoning system and distill knowledge for robot learning.

## **Education**

Arizona State University

Ph.D. in Computer Science, Advisor: Prof. Heni Ben Amor Aug. 2019 - May. 2024

• Thesis Focus: Robot Learning via Deep State-Space Modeling GPA: 4.0/4.0

**Case Western Reserve University** 

M.S. IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING, ADVISOR: PROF. KIJU LEE Aug. 2016 - May. 2019

• Thesis Focus: Automated Facial Emotion Recognition for Human-Robot Interaction GPA: 3.8/4.0

**Southwest Jiaotong University** 

B.S. IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

Aug. 2011 - May. 2015

• Project: Fault Diagnosis of Roller Bearing Based on Wavelet Analysis GPA: 3.6/4.0

**Experience** 

RadiusAl, Inc.

COMPUTER VISION DATA SCIENTIST (PART-TIME)

Sep. 2020 - Dec 2023

Tempe, Arizona

Tempe, Arizona

- Refined Multi-object tracking (MOT) algorithms using Bayes Filter for Video Analytics for indoor and outdoor cameras, improved ~9% accuracy.
- Developed multi-objective optimization technique base on Frank-Wolfe algorithm for monocular depth prediction model across multiple datasets.
- Researched on monocular depth prediction models with varied advanced architecture, Vision Transformer and multi-scale local planar guidance blocks, achieved depth estimation with 0.117, 0.416 on abs REL and RMS error metrics and 0.868 on d1 metric on NYU depth testset.

### **Interactive Robtoics Lab, ASU**

Tempe, Arizona

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE

June. 2020 - Present

- Developed state-space modeling for long-horizon robot learning within Large Language models (LLMs), where LLMs perform planning and reasoning
  while maintaining state tracking.
- Embodied AI: Proposed Diff-Control, an Action diffusion policy incorporating ControlNet from the domain of image generation to robot actions. [C7]
- Created a multimodal learning framework ( $\alpha$ -MDF) using attention mechanism and differentiable filtering, which conducts state estimation in latent space with multiple modalities. **[C5]**
- Developed differentiable Ensemble Kalman Filters (DEnKF) framework incorporating algorithmic priors for robot learning, i.e., learning system dynamics from observations, and learning representations from high-dimensional space. [C4]
- Deployed the differentiable filtering framework with smartwatch for ubiquitous robot control tasks, i.e., teleoperation, drone piloting. [C6]

### **Case Western Reserve University**

Cleveland, Ohio

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Aug. 2017 - Aug. 2019

- Led social robot project "Woody and Philos" project, developed advanced algorithms in Computer Vision for social robots. [C2]
- Real-time Human Facial Emotion Expression Recognition for Human-robot Interaction using deep learning and machine learning technique. (featured on Case Western Daily) [C1] [J1]
- Human-Robot Interaction: Developed social robots—"Philos" & "Woody" platform and investigated the potential of social robots as cognitive assessment applications for older adults. (featured on ideastream)
- Human-centered Al: Collaborated on hardware and algorithm development for the vision-based Tangible Geometric Games- "e-Cube" for cognitive skills assessment.

#### **CWRU & ASU**

Cleveland, Ohio & Tempe, Arizona

TEACHING ASSISTENT

2018 - 2019, 2023 - 2024

- Served as the teaching assistant for EMAE250 (Computers in Mechanical Engineering), instructing students on numerical problem-solving using Matlab and providing guidance throughout the learning process.
- TA for CSE205 (Object Oriented Programming), instructing students on conding with varied data structure and OOP tasks in Java.

JULY 7, 2024 XIAO LIU · CV

Uber Technologies, Inc. Xi'an, China

DATA ANALYST Jan. 2016 - Aug. 2016

· Coordinated data analysis and fraud detection with the operation team. Conducted competitor tracking and advising on driver incentives.

Hitachi, Ltd.

**DESIGN ENGINEER** June 2015 - Dec. 2015

· Assisted in product development by analyzing cable and power converter sizing, heat release, and power supply design. Revised design parameters to meet customer requirements and national standards while optimizing manufacturing and logistical processes for cost reduction.

# **Publications**

2024	[\$1], Zhou, Y, Liu, X, Vuong, Q & Ben Amor, H. "AutoMA: Automated Modular Attention enables Context-Rich	CoRL 2024
	Imitation Learning using Foundation Models" 8th Conference on Robot Learning (under review)	CURL 2024
2024	[C7], Liu, X, Zhou, Y, Weigend, F, Sonawani, S, Ikemoto, S & Ben Amor, H. "Diff-Control: A Stateful Diffusion-based	IROS 2024
	Policy for Imitation Learning" IEEE/RSJ IROS	IKUS 2024
2024	[W2], Liu, X, Weigend, F, Zhou, Y & Ben Amor, H. "Enabling Stateful Behaviors for Diffusion-based Policy	ICRA 2024
	Learning" ICRA 2024 Workshop - Back to the Future: Robot Learning Going Probabilistic	ICRA 2024
2024	[C6], Weigend, F, Liu, X, Sonawani, S & Ben Amor, H. "iRoCo: Intuitive Robot Control from Anywhere using a	ICRA 2024
	Smartwatch" IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)	ICRA 2024
2023	[W2], Liu, X, Zhou, Y, Ikemoto, S & Ben Amor, H. "Multimodal Learning of Soft Robot Dynamics using	CoRL 2023
	Differentiable Filters" CoRL 2023 Workshop on Learning for Soft Robots	CONL 2023
2023	<b>[C5]</b> , $\underline{\text{Liu}}$ , X, Zhou, Y, Ikemoto, S & Ben Amor, H. " $\alpha$ -MDF: An Attention-based Multimodal Differentiable Filter for	CoRL 2023
	Robot State Estimation" 7th Conference on Robot Learning	CONL 2023
2023	[W1], Weigend, F, Liu, X, & Ben Amor, H. "Probabilistic Differentiable Filters Enable Ubiquitous Robot Control	IROS 2023
	with Smartwatches" IROS 2023 Workshop on Differentiable Probabilistic Robotics	11.03 2023
2023	[C4], Liu, X, Clark, G, Campbell, J, Zhou, Y & Ben Amor, H. "Enhancing State Estimation in Robots: A Data-Driven	IROS 2023
	Approach with Differentiable Ensemble Kalman Filters" IEEE/RSJ IROS	11.03 2023
2023	[C3], Liu, X, Ikemoto, S, Yoshimitsu, Y & Ben Amor, H. "Learning Soft Robot Dynamics using Differentiable Kalman	IROS 2023
	Filters and Spatio-Temporal Embeddings" IEEE/RSJ IROS	11103 2023
2021	[J1], Liu, X, Cheng, X & Lee, K. "GA and SVM based Facial Emotion Recognition using Geometric Features" IEEE	IFFF sensors 2021
	sensors Journal on Machine Vision and automated systems	1222 3C113013 2021
2020	[C2], Hayosh D, Liu, X & Lee, K. "Woody: Low-Cost Open-source Humanoid Torso Robot" <i>IEEE 17th International</i>	UR 2020
	Conference on Ubiquitous Robots (UR)	ON 2020
2020	[C1], Liu, X & Lee, K. "Optimized Facial Emotion Recognition Technique for Assessing User Experience" IEEE	GEM 2020
	Games Entertainment and Medias Conference (GEM)	GLIVI 2020

# Skills

Kiju Lee

• Programming: Python, C/C++, Java; Tools & Library: PyTorch, TensorFlow, OpenCV, ROS, Matlab, MuJoCo, Unity, Docker, Git, Kubernetes;

# References

**Heni Ben Amor** Tempe, Arizona

ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR, Ph.D. Advisor

Arizona State University

• School of Computing and Augmented Intelligence | Google DeepMind Researcher Tel: 480.965.2253, Email: hbenamor@asu.edu

ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR, M.S. ADVISOR Texas A&M University

• Engineering Technology and Industrial Distribution and Mechanical Engineering Tel: 979.458.6479, Email: kiju.lee@tamu.edu

**Wenlong Zhang** Mesa, Arizona

ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR, Ph.D. COMMITTEE MEMBER

Arizona State University

School of Manufacturing Systems and Networks at the Ira A. Fulton Schools of Engineering Email: Wenlong. Zhang@asu.edu

**Aykut Dengi** Tempe, Arizona

CEO, INDUSTRY ADVISOR RadiusAl

• Co-founder, Co-CEO, and Board Member, RadiusAl Tel: 480.540.1349, Email: aykut.dengi@radius.ai